<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the parish-church of St. Mary Saviour's in Southwark, at the Lent-assizes, Feb. 28, 1671 before the honourable Sir Thomas Twisden, and Sir William Morton, His Majesties judges of assize, and at the request of Ellis Crisp, Esq., high sheriff of the county of Surrey / by Thomas Horton, D.D.</title>
            <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43265</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27098309</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27098309</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44569)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1721:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the parish-church of St. Mary Saviour's in Southwark, at the Lent-assizes, Feb. 28, 1671 before the honourable Sir Thomas Twisden, and Sir William Morton, His Majesties judges of assize, and at the request of Ellis Crisp, Esq., high sheriff of the county of Surrey / by Thomas Horton, D.D.</title>
                  <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.R. for Ralph Smith, at the Bible, under the Piazzo of the Royal Exchange in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 2nd, XIX, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109969:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the <hi>Pariſh-Church</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Mary Saviour's IN SOUTHWARK At the <hi>Lent-Aſſizes,</hi> Febr. 28. 1671.</p>
            <p>BEFORE THE <hi>HONOVRABLE</hi> S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi> Thomas Twiſden AND S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi> William Morton His MAJESTIES Judges of ASSIZE. AND At the Requeſt of <hi>Ellis Criſp</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> High Sheriff of the County of SURREY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Horton</hi> D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 21.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>To do Juſtice and Judgment is more acceptable to the Lord then Sacrifice.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 7.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Judge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous Judgment.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W.R.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Bible,</hi> under the <hi>Piazzo</hi> of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:109969:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109969:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED BEFORE THE JUDGES The Eight and Twentieth of <hi>February,</hi> 1671.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Chron. 19.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he ſaid to the Judges, Take heed what ye do, for ye judge not for Man, but for the LORD, who is with you in the Judgment.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere is nothing more comely, or amiable, then when <hi>Worth</hi> goes together with <hi>Honour,</hi> and when <hi>Places</hi> of <hi>Truſt</hi> and Dignity meet with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109969:3"/>
               <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> and Integrity for the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aging</hi> and diſcharge of them, from whence they prove to be mutually <hi>acceptable,</hi> and advantagious one to the other. This is that which is obſervable of us in the carriage and ſcope of this Scripture which we have now before us, where <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> the King of <hi>Judah</hi> finding it to be in ſome Reſpects <hi>requiſite</hi> and neceſſary for Him to ſet up certain Officers of <hi>State,</hi> and to appoint <hi>Judges</hi> in the Land, for the better ruling and governing of his Kingdom under <hi>himſelf:</hi> He does not content himſelf only to appoint them their <hi>Places,</hi> but he is careful alſo to mind them of their <hi>Duties,</hi> and to provoke them to care and <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> in theſe places which were impoſed upon them, and ſuſtain'd by them: That they might be the better inabled to give <hi>their</hi> Charge to <hi>others,</hi> he firſt of all gives <hi>his</hi> Charge to <hi>them,</hi> and lays a very ſtrict and ſolemn Injunction upon them. That ſo from the ſame Authority whence they received their <hi>Office</hi> it ſelf, they might likewiſe receive ſome kind of <hi>fitneſs</hi> and preparation for it; <hi>And be ſaid unto the Judges, Take heed what ye do, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words there are two main parts conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of us. Firſt, A <hi>Charge</hi> premiſed. Secondly, A <hi>Reaſon</hi> annext for the inforcing of this Charge. The <hi>Charge,</hi> that we have in theſe words, <hi>Take heed what
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109969:3"/>ye do.</hi> The <hi>Reaſon</hi> annext in theſe, <hi>For ye judge not, &amp;c.</hi> Or if ye will, we may <hi>invert</hi> the parts, and take them thus; Firſt, A <hi>Truth</hi> declared. Secondly, A <hi>Caution</hi> inferred upon the ſuppoſition and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this Truth. The <hi>Truth</hi> declared in theſe words, <hi>Ye judge not, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Caution</hi> infer'd in theſe, <hi>Take heed what ye do.</hi> So as the one is in the nature of <hi>the Doctrine,</hi> the other of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> And in this method and order ſhall I now with Gods gracious aſſiſtance take notice of them; I begin firſt of all with the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> which is the <hi>Doctrine</hi> or Truth declared, and this conſiſting of <hi>two</hi> Branches more; Firſt, The ſimple <hi>Prepoſition.</hi> Secondly, The additional <hi>Ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> The <hi>Prepoſition,</hi> that ye have in thoſe words, <hi>Ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord.</hi> The <hi>Ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> that ye have in theſe, <hi>Who is with you in the Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Here is conſiderable of us the ſimple or ſingle <hi>Prepoſition, Ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord:</hi> This is that which is here aſſerted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared concerning the <hi>Judges.</hi> But it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ems to carry ſome kind of difficulty and intricacy with it, and therefore will require a little opening and explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it to us, in what ſenſe it is to be taken by us. The <hi>Prepoſition</hi> it ſelf is of that nature as wherein the Parts are <hi>ſegregated</hi> and ſeparated one from the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109969:4"/>other, and accordingly we ſhall ſpeak ſeparately and <hi>diſtinctly</hi> of them. Firſt, By ſhewing how far the Judges <hi>do</hi> indeed judge or <hi>not</hi> judge for <hi>Man.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Shewing how far and in what reſpects they do judge for the <hi>Lord.</hi> For there is a Truth contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>in both,</hi> being rightly ſtated and underſtood by us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To view it in the <hi>firſt</hi> reference, as it hath reſpect unto <hi>Men:</hi> Judges they do in a ſenſe, and in ſome ſort, judge even <hi>thus;</hi> They judge for <hi>Man,</hi> and that according to a <hi>twofold</hi> explication: Firſt, For Man, that is, by Mans <hi>Appointment, Hominum Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuto.</hi> Secondly, For <hi>Man,</hi> that is, for Mans <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, Hominum Commodo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, For Man, that is, by the <hi>Appointment</hi> of Man: They judge <hi>ſo,</hi> and ſo <hi>they may</hi> judge: It is true, They are by <hi>Gods</hi> appointment <hi>chiefly,</hi> as we ſhall hear afterwards out of the <hi>Text,</hi> but they are by <hi>Man's</hi> alſo <hi>ſubordinately;</hi> and therefore even here in this preſent Scripture are ſaid ſo to be. In the verſe immediately preceeding, namely, the <hi>fifth</hi> verſe of this Chapter, it is ſaid, That <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſet up Judges in the Land, throughout all the fenced Cities of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> City by City. And <hi>ſo Moſes</hi> by the advice of <hi>Jethro,</hi> choſe able men out of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and they <hi>judged</hi> the People at all Seaſons, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.25, 26.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109969:4"/>And ſo <hi>Samuel,</hi> upon the ſame account alſo he judged <hi>Iſrael</hi> all his Dayes, and went from year to year <hi>in Circuit,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.15, 16. <hi>Judges</hi> they are <hi>no new</hi> thing in the World, but have been long appointed, and that by <hi>Men</hi> themſelves: Therefore expreſly call'd in Scripture the Ordinance <hi>of Man,</hi> or <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Creation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man, for the Lords ſake,</hi> whether <hi>it be unto the King, as Supream,</hi> or <hi>unto Governors that are ſent by him.</hi> Theſe <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors,</hi> amongſt the reſt, are the <hi>Judges,</hi> who are there deſcribed, from the main ſcope of their Office, in reference either to <hi>Puniſhment</hi> or <hi>to Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, For <hi>Man,</hi> that is, for Mans <hi>Advantage;</hi> They judge for man likewiſe <hi>ſo:</hi> for man, that is, for the <hi>good</hi> of man, and as that which <hi>is beneficial</hi> to him, for ſo it is. <hi>Judges,</hi> and the Diſpencers of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> they are of very great <hi>uſe and neceſsity</hi> in the life of <hi>Man,</hi> without which he could not well <hi>ſubſiſt</hi> or hold out in the World, nor indeed the <hi>World</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it ſelf. <hi>Man</hi> by nature is ſo <hi>wild a</hi> Creature, and hath ſo much corruption and perverſneſs in his heart, as that without <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> People would be ready to deſtroy both <hi>themſelves</hi> and <hi>one another.</hi> Therefore we have very great cauſe to bleſs God for ſuch as <hi>theſe,</hi> and to ſubmit unto them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109969:5"/>as being indeed <hi>our own</hi> greateſt Intereſt and Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation: For it is the happineſs of every thing which is <hi>inferior,</hi> to be in <hi>ſubordination</hi> to an <hi>higher</hi> than it ſelf, for the regulating and ordering of it: And the <hi>weaker</hi> that any thing is, by ſo much the more does it <hi>need</hi> the power of another to <hi>ſupport</hi> and aſſiſt it. Therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> ſayes, He is <hi>the Minister of God to thee for good,</hi> Rom. 13.4. that is, he is ſo by <hi>his Place and Office</hi> in the proper nature and ſcope of it. And for <hi>good</hi> in the full <hi>latitude,</hi> and extent of <hi>goodneſs:</hi> God in <hi>mercy</hi> and favor to <hi>Man,</hi> hath appointed <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and Governors to Rule him, and <hi>Judges</hi> to paſs Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon him; and therefore accordingly hath commanded that they ſhould <hi>be acknowledged</hi> and <hi>prayed</hi> for by him, 1 Tim. 2.1, 2. <hi>I exhort that Supplications and Prayers, and Interceſſions and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Thanks be made for all men, for Kings and for all that are in Authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> Which word <hi>that,</hi> is to be taken not onely <hi>Intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliter,</hi> but <hi>Conſecutive;</hi> not onely as ſhewing the <hi>End</hi> or Reaſon <hi>why</hi> we ſhould make ſuch Prayers, but alſo as ſhewing the <hi>Effect or Conſequent</hi> of ſuch Prayers being made, and the good which does fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from <hi>ſuch Perſons</hi> for whom they are made. And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109969:5"/>thus have we ſeen in what ſenſe it does indeed hold good, That <hi>Judges do judge for Man;</hi> which is <hi>twofold,</hi> Firſt, For <hi>Man,</hi> that is, by Man's <hi>Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Hominum Inſtituto.</hi> And ſecondly, For <hi>Man,</hi> that is, for Man's <hi>Advantage, Hominum Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remains now further in the next place, that we ſhould look upon it in the <hi>Negative,</hi> and ſee how far it does <hi>not</hi> hold as it is declared to us here directly and expreſly in the very words of the <hi>Text, They judge not for Man:</hi> Now this, it may be thus far explicated and unfolded unto us; Firſt, Not for <hi>Man</hi> in an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive</hi> ſenſe, not for Man <hi>onely.</hi> Secondly, Not for <hi>Man</hi> in a <hi>Superlative</hi> ſenſe, not for Man <hi>chiefly.</hi> Thirdly, Not for <hi>Man</hi> in an <hi>Irregular</hi> or Inordinate ſenſe, not for Man <hi>corruptly;</hi> neither of theſe wayes for <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Not for <hi>Man</hi> in an <hi>Excluſive</hi> ſenſe, not for Man <hi>onely:</hi> Judges they do in ſome reſpects (as we have ſhewn) judge for <hi>Man,</hi> but they do not judge for Man <hi>alone.</hi> There is an <hi>higher</hi> who is to be look'd at, and regarded in their Judgment; and whom ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it concerns them to <hi>approve</hi> and to acquit themſelves to; They may not think that when they have ſatisfied <hi>Men,</hi> and done that onely which <hi>they</hi> required of them, that they have diſcharged their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109969:6"/>
               <hi>Duty,</hi> but muſt conſider moreover, that they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable and accountable <hi>to God,</hi> who will alſo <hi>take</hi> an account of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not for Man in a <hi>Superlative</hi> ſenſe, not for Man <hi>chieſty:</hi> Judges they judge for <hi>Man,</hi> but in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place, not in the <hi>firſt;</hi> they judge for <hi>Man</hi> as the <hi>ſubject</hi> and <hi>object</hi> of their Judgment which it is exerciſed and converſant <hi>about;</hi> judge <hi>betwixt man and man,</hi> as the Scripture expreſſes it: But <hi>man</hi> is not the main <hi>End</hi> or Scope of their Judgment which it is carryed and directed unto, but a <hi>greater</hi> Perſon; they judge for <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>reference</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>his</hi> account, and ſuch conſiderations as theſe: And therefore we are required to <hi>ſubmit</hi> unto them <hi>for the Lords ſake,</hi> in the place before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
            <p>It is a <hi>rule</hi> in the expoſition of Scripture, That <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parationes negativae non excludunt ſed praeponunt;</hi> That <hi>negative</hi> Compariſons they do not <hi>exclude</hi> one part, but <hi>prefer</hi> another: As for example, where it is ſaid, God will have <hi>Mercy</hi> and not <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> the meaning is not, that he will not have <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> but that (in ſuch caſes) he will <hi>rather</hi> have Mercy. So when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays of himſelf, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſent him him not to <hi>Baptize,</hi> but to <hi>Preach</hi> the Goſpel: It was not as <hi>prohibiting</hi> Baptiſme, but as preferring
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109969:6"/>
               <hi>Preaching:</hi> Again, when it is ſaid of <hi>Servants,</hi> As doing Service to the <hi>Lord</hi> and not unto <hi>Man;</hi> it is not as excluding <hi>Man,</hi> but as extolling <hi>God:</hi> To the Lord, and <hi>not</hi> unto <hi>Man;</hi> that is, to the Lord <hi>rather</hi> than unto <hi>Man;</hi> and ſo <hi>here</hi> now in the <hi>Text, Ye judge not for man, but for the Lord;</hi> that is, not for man <hi>ſo much</hi> as for the <hi>Lord:</hi> Not for <hi>man</hi> in a <hi>Superlative</hi> ſenſe, for man principally or <hi>chiefly,</hi> ye judge not for man <hi>ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Not for <hi>man</hi> in an <hi>irregular</hi> or inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſenſe; not for man <hi>corruptly,</hi> ye judge not for <hi>man;</hi> that is, not for the meer <hi>will</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> of man, Non <hi>Hominibus,</hi> i. e. Non <hi>Hominum arbitrio.</hi> Judges in the adminiſtration of Judgment are not to make it their buſineſs to pleaſe and gratifie <hi>men,</hi> or to do nothing but what may be acceptable and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory <hi>to them.</hi> Theſe that <hi>thus</hi> ſeek to pleaſe ſuch, they are not the Servants <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 1.10. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>general</hi> of all <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> it holds more particularly and eſpecially of ſuch kind of <hi>Perſons,</hi> that they ſhould <hi>not live to the luſts of men, but to the will of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.3. It is a dangerous thing for any Perſons whatſoever to make <hi>men</hi> to be the abſolute <hi>rule</hi> and byaſs of their <hi>Actions,</hi> as being compaſt with very <hi>much infirmity:</hi> But it is to <hi>none</hi> more dangerous then it is to thoſe who are in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109969:7"/>Places of <hi>Judicature</hi> and Publick Government; to ſuch as thoſe it is more hazardous than to any <hi>other</hi> beſides. And therefore it is that the Scripture does lay ſo many ſtrict <hi>Cautions</hi> and Prohibitions to his purpoſe of having regard <hi>to man</hi> in ſuch matters as theſe are. Thus Levit. 19.25. <hi>Thou ſhalt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the perſon of the Poor, nor honor the perſon of the Mighty, but in Righteouſneſs ſhalt thou judge thy Neighbour.</hi> So Deut. 1.17. <hi>Ye ſhall not reſpect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Judgment, but ye ſhall hear the Small as well as the Great: Ye ſhall not be afraid of the face of man, for the Judgment is Gods.</hi> Again, Deut. 16.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not wreſt Judgment, Thou ſhall not reſpect Perſons.</hi> In all theſe places, and the like, is <hi>man</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from an <hi>abſolute</hi> influence upon ſuch a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as this is, as whereby it ſhould be <hi>regulated</hi> or <hi>determin'd</hi> And ſo are we now to take it here in the <hi>Text</hi> in this expreſſion before us, <hi>Ye judge not for man,</hi> that is, not for the <hi>fear</hi> of man, ſo as to be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified <hi>by that. Ye judge not for man,</hi> that is, not for the <hi>ſavor</hi> of man, ſo as to be tickl'd <hi>by that. Ye judge not for man,</hi> that is, not for the <hi>fancy</hi> of man, ſo as to <hi>be led or guided by that:</hi> not for <hi>man;</hi> that is, not for mans <hi>luſt</hi> and <hi>humour,</hi> and <hi>extravagancy,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate affection:</hi> Not for <hi>man</hi> in any caſe, <hi>ſo</hi> by any <hi>means.</hi> The word <hi>Man</hi> in Scripture-Language is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109969:7"/>ſometimes uſed as <hi>Terminus Diminuens,</hi> as carrying ſome kind of <hi>diſparagement</hi> and diminution with it. Thus 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. Are ye not <hi>carnal,</hi> and walk as <hi>man,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And accordingly in <hi>this</hi> Notion is it conſiderable of us here in this place, as to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in hand: And ſo ye have ſeen this paſſage in the full ſenſe and explication of it here, and in what reſpects it is here ſaid, That <hi>ye do not judge for man;</hi> that is, not for man <hi>onely</hi> but for the Lord <hi>alſo;</hi> not for man <hi>chiefly,</hi> but for the Lord <hi>rather;</hi> not for man <hi>abſolutely and indefinitely,</hi> and at large, howſoever conſider'd or qualified, but in ſubmiſſion and ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination <hi>to the Lord;</hi> for <hi>man</hi> in complyance <hi>with</hi> God, but not in <hi>contradiction</hi> to him, or <hi>oppoſition againſt</hi> him. And ſo much may ſuffice to have ſpoken of this <hi>Judgment</hi> in its <hi>firſt</hi> reference, as it hath reſpect unto <hi>man,</hi> which we have ſeen both in the <hi>Affirmative and Negative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> reference of it is, as it hath reſpect <hi>to God,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>But for the LORD.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> as well as <hi>the former</hi> doth admit of <hi>various</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications; we may take them briefly thus;</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the Lord <hi>Authoritatively,</hi> by Warrant and <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from <hi>Him.</hi> They are appointed by <hi>man</hi> (as I ſhewed before) <hi>immediately,</hi> but by God <hi>originally.</hi> They take their <hi>Office</hi> firſt of all from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109969:8"/>
               <hi>Him,</hi> who is the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Owner</hi> of it: Therefore ſaith <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> that is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the <hi>eſſential</hi> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Father, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>By me Kings Reign, and Princes decree Juſtice: By me Princes Rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the Earth.</hi> It is ſaid in <hi>Judges</hi> 2.16. That the <hi>Lord raiſed up Judges,</hi> and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.11. That <hi>he commanded Judges:</hi> And here in the <hi>Text,</hi> it was not <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> only of himſelf, but probably by direction from <hi>God:</hi> Therefore, together with other <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> they are call'd expreſly, The <hi>Miniſters of God,</hi> Rom. 14.4. Are ſaid to be ordain'd <hi>of God,</hi> which is accordingly made to be <hi>a ground</hi> for <hi>obedience</hi> and ſubjection to them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the Lord <hi>repreſentatively,</hi> in the Lord's <hi>ſtead:</hi> Judges and Magiſtrates they are in the room and <hi>place</hi> of God, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſometime ſpake of <hi>himſelf</hi> to his <hi>Brethen, Gen.</hi> 50.19. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſometimes alſo have they <hi>the name</hi> of <hi>God</hi> faſten'd upon them, <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82.6. They are <hi>Dii nuncupative,</hi> though not <hi>formaliter.</hi> And they are <hi>Dii participative,</hi> though not <hi>eſſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter:</hi> God hath ſtampt his <hi>own Power and Authority</hi> in part upon them, which they do execute for <hi>his</hi> ſake, and in reference <hi>to him:</hi> Therefore it was the Speech of the Lord to <hi>Moſes</hi> concerning <hi>Aaron</hi> his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109969:8"/>Brother, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.16. <hi>And he ſhall be thy Spokeſman unto the People: And he ſhall be even to thee in ſtead of a Mouth, and thou ſhalt be to him in ſtead of God;</hi> that is, <hi>he</hi> ſhall be <hi>thine Interpreter;</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> ſhalt be his <hi>Governor,</hi> to reveal my <hi>will</hi> unto him, and <hi>Power to Command him:</hi> This is order'd in great <hi>goodneſs</hi> and kindneſs to the <hi>Sons of Men;</hi> Look as in the Work of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> it is a <hi>favour</hi> that God ſpeaks to us <hi>by man,</hi> and not by <hi>himſelf</hi> (Let <hi>Moſes ſpeak to us, and we will hear him, but let not God ſpeak to us, leaſt we die,</hi> Exod. 20.19.) So here as to the work of the <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> it is a favour that God <hi>judges</hi> us by <hi>man,</hi> and not <hi>by himſelf:</hi> For ſo he does now here in this preſent World; indeed in the World to <hi>come,</hi> then he will judge men by <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> more immediately, but for the <hi>preſent</hi> he does it by <hi>his Officers. Man</hi> is now judged by his <hi>Peers,</hi> who <hi>judge</hi> for the <hi>Lord,</hi> as <hi>repreſenting</hi> him in this Judgment, <hi>Domino,</hi> i. e. <hi>Loco Domini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, For the Lord <hi>effectually</hi> or intentionally, for the Lord's <hi>Interest:</hi> God hath therefore appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Judges and Magiſtrates, and ſuch kind of Perſons in the world, that ſo from thence his <hi>own</hi> Honour might be <hi>preſerved</hi> more inviolably in it; That his <hi>Commands</hi> might be the more <hi>regarded,</hi> and his <hi>Laws</hi> might take the greater <hi>place</hi> in the Hearts of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109969:9"/>
               <hi>Ye judge for the Lord;</hi> as by your <hi>places</hi> in the right <hi>diſcharge</hi> of them, ye bring more <hi>glory</hi> to God then <hi>other</hi> men do. The <hi>higher</hi> that any are <hi>in Place,</hi> the greater <hi>in Influence,</hi> and they have larger <hi>oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities</hi> of doing good afforded unto them; which is indeed, if it be duely conſider'd, the greateſt <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and advantage</hi> of them. Oh what a great deal of good hath a good <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> occaſion to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh, for the reſtraining <hi>of Vice,</hi> for the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Virtues,</hi> and every way for the advancing of the <hi>Name</hi> of God in the World! There is no man that does the <hi>leaſt</hi> good, but he ſerves the <hi>Lord</hi> in it in ſome <hi>meaſure:</hi> But thoſe that do <hi>ſuch</hi> good as <hi>this</hi> is, they do ſerve <hi>Him</hi> in it more <hi>eſpecically.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Sin</hi> in the proper nature of it, but ſome more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſtrikes at the very <hi>Majeſty</hi> of God, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes his <hi>Intereſt:</hi> Therefore <hi>Judges</hi> whiles they ſet themſelves againſt Sin, they do ſo far forth act <hi>for God;</hi> for the <hi>Lord</hi> Emphatically. And ſo now I have done with the <hi>firſt</hi> Branch of this <hi>firſt general,</hi> to wit, the ſimple or ſingle <hi>Propoſition</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>Ye judge not for man, but for the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the additional <hi>amplification,</hi> in thoſe, <hi>Who is with you in the Judgment:</hi> This is added, to make the Declaration ſo much the more <hi>conſiderable,</hi> and to <hi>quicken</hi> theſe Judges in this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109969:9"/>their <hi>Office,</hi> which was undertaken by them: But how does this hold <hi>good,</hi> and in what <hi>ſenſe</hi> is it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? Take it if you pleaſe <hi>thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, He is with you to <hi>behold</hi> you, to obſerve you, and to take notice of you: He is <hi>with you,</hi> that is, he is <hi>preſent</hi> amongſt you, and <hi>ſees all</hi> that is done by you; <hi>God ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty, he judgeth among the gods,</hi> Pſal. 82.1. <hi>Amongſt</hi> them, or in the <hi>midst</hi> of them, as the words run in <hi>the Text,</hi> where any Perſons are gather'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <hi>in his Name,</hi> there is He in <hi>the midſt</hi> amongſt them. It holds good not onely of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Aſſemblies, but alſo of <hi>Judicial.</hi> As for King <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat,</hi> who <hi>appointed</hi> and ſet up theſe Judges, <hi>He</hi> could not be <hi>alwayes</hi> or <hi>every</hi> where with them <hi>himſelf,</hi> nor have his <hi>Eye continually</hi> upon them: <hi>He</hi> could not perfectly take notice of the things which were tranſacted by them; but he tells them, That the <hi>Lord</hi> was with them, and ſo conſequently that he <hi>ſaw</hi> and <hi>beheld</hi> them, which was more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edrable to them, then any thing elſe: <hi>As his Eyes are with Kings upon the Throne,</hi> Job 36.7. So alſo with <hi>Judges</hi> upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> as being <hi>himſelf</hi> the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> of all: He is <hi>with you</hi> in the Judgment to <hi>behold</hi> you, That's the <hi>firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:109969:10"/>
            <p>Secondly, He is with you to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> you, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able you, and to be helpful to you: He is <hi>with you,</hi> not onely in your <hi>Perſons,</hi> but alſo in your <hi>Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and in your <hi>Work,</hi> to promote you <hi>in it,</hi> and carry you <hi>through it.</hi> This is that which is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite</hi> and neceſſary to <hi>every</hi> buſineſs that we take in hand, which is of any <hi>conſequence;</hi> but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſuch a buſineſs as <hi>this</hi> is, which we now mention. And it is that which is here graciouſly <hi>promiſed</hi> to ſuch Perſons as theſe are, in the exerciſe of their <hi>Judiciary proceedings:</hi> This we may conceive him to be <hi>two</hi> manner of wayes, Either firſt of all, by way of <hi>general</hi> and habitual <hi>Qualification:</hi> Or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by way of <hi>actual</hi> and particular <hi>Aſſiſtance.</hi> The <hi>former,</hi> by inabling them <hi>for</hi> their work: The <hi>latter,</hi> by inabling them <hi>in it.</hi> And this <hi>latter</hi> as well as the <hi>former</hi> is that which is much to be <hi>prized</hi> and regarded by them: It is <hi>that</hi> which is very needful and deſirable in <hi>all other</hi> profeſſions &amp; Employments beſides. For <hi>God</hi> is not onely to be with them <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motely</hi> by a <hi>common</hi> and general <hi>Preparation,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be with them <hi>immediately</hi> by a <hi>particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence.</hi> Thus (for inſtance) a <hi>Preacher,</hi> he does not onely need a qualification <hi>in general,</hi> for the work of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> but alſo God's aſſiſtance in every <hi>particular Sermon;</hi> Nor a <hi>Souldier</hi> does not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109969:10"/>need onely to be train'd up to the War in <hi>general,</hi> but to have aſſiſtance in <hi>every Battell:</hi> Nor a <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> to have Skill <hi>at large,</hi> and in the <hi>habit,</hi> but to have <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> as to ſuch a particular <hi>Patient,</hi> and to ſuch a particular Diſeaſe; And as is ſaid of our bleſſed Saviour, To have Power <hi>preſent</hi> with him <hi>to Heal.</hi> And ſo for <hi>Judges,</hi> and the Diſtributers of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> not only to be <hi>able men</hi> in the Law &amp; Affairs of Judicature, conſider'd at <hi>large,</hi> but alſo to be <hi>aſſiſted</hi> by God in ſuch particular <hi>Cauſes,</hi> and in ſuch particular <hi>Caſes,</hi> and in ſuch particular <hi>Difficulties</hi> which are at any time <hi>brought</hi> before them. And this (as I conceive) is included alſo in <hi>his being with them;</hi> and from <hi>God</hi> in the mouth of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> intimated and <hi>declared</hi> unto them. That which is here rendred, <hi>In the Judgment,</hi> is in the Text <hi>Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var Miſhphat,</hi> which according to a different ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath a <hi>double</hi> ſenſe with it: This word it ſignifies both <hi>Res</hi> and <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum:</hi> And each of them very <hi>pertinent</hi> to the purpoſe in hand. God promiſing aſſiſtance to theſe <hi>Judges</hi> in each particular; Firſt, He is with you <hi>in re Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicii,</hi> that is, in the <hi>matter</hi> of the Judgment, as the <hi>Margin</hi> expreſſes it: He is with you to inable you to <hi>judge aright,</hi> and to diſcern of <hi>the Cauſe</hi> and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs it ſelf which is offer'd and <hi>preſented</hi> to you.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109969:11"/>Secondly, He is with you <hi>in verbo judicii,</hi> that is, he is with you in the <hi>Sentence</hi> and Verdict which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by you, and which comes from you. As in each of theſe you do <hi>need his</hi> aſſiſtance, ſo in each of theſe you have the <hi>promiſe of his aſſiſtance made over</hi> to you, upon your <hi>dependence</hi> upon him for it: He is <hi>with</hi> you, ſo as to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> you, and to <hi>inable</hi> you; That's the <hi>Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, He is with you, <hi>to defend you;</hi> not only to ſtand <hi>among</hi> you, but alſo to ſtand <hi>by</hi> you, and <hi>to</hi> ſtand to you: This is that which is to be <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> and taken for granted, that thoſe who are in any kind <hi>hinderers</hi> and reſtrainers <hi>of Sin,</hi> they ſhall be ſure to have Enemies, <hi>Miniſters</hi> that reprove and <hi>condemn</hi> it, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> that cenſure and <hi>puniſh</hi> it: And therefore accordingly will they <hi>need</hi> ſuch as may be <hi>Abettors</hi> to them. This is that which <hi>God</hi> himſelf does <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake</hi> here for theſe <hi>Judges;</hi> That he will <hi>thus</hi> be <hi>with them,</hi> and that according to a <hi>twofold</hi> injury, whereunto they are expoſed from thoſe who are Enemies to them: The one is of <hi>Reproach</hi> and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy, the <hi>ſtrife of Tongues.</hi> The other is of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault</hi> and Miſchief, the <hi>Hand of Violence:</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had <hi>to each</hi> of theſe will God be <hi>with them</hi> to <hi>defend them:</hi> He will defend their <hi>Names,</hi> to <hi>juſtifie</hi> them, and he will defend their <hi>Perſons,</hi> to <hi>protect</hi> them, and to keep them <hi>from evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:109969:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, Their <hi>Names</hi> to <hi>juſtice</hi> them, where they are careful to diſcharge their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and to do that in good <hi>earneſt</hi> which is their <hi>Duty;</hi> they ſhall be ſure to have <hi>Him</hi> with them <hi>thus,</hi> ſo as to <hi>clear</hi> them, and to take off thoſe <hi>Scandals</hi> which are paſt upon them: While men ſeek to pleaſe <hi>men,</hi> and to curry favour with <hi>them,</hi> God does many times, in <hi>juſt</hi> Judgment, give them up to the <hi>cenſures</hi> of men, and make them more <hi>odious</hi> and abominable; But while they are careful to diſcharge their <hi>Duty,</hi> he does from thence clear <hi>their Innocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Their <hi>Perſons</hi> to protect them; there are ſometimes <hi>deſperate</hi> People in the world, who by their <hi>inſolency,</hi> and violent attempts, would <hi>fright</hi> thoſe who are the <hi>Diſpenſers</hi> of Juſtice, from that which is to be done by them; but God <hi>himſelf</hi> takes <hi>care</hi> of them, and <hi>watches</hi> over them. Thoſe who are publick <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> they are under a more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial <hi>Protection;</hi> and <hi>thoſe Angels</hi> which are charged <hi>with others,</hi> do take more <hi>ſpecial</hi> charge of <hi>them</hi> then of any others beſides: God is <hi>with</hi> them, to <hi>defend</hi> and <hi>preſerve</hi> them on every ſide; to hide them in the <hi>ſecret of his preſence,</hi> from the <hi>pride of man,</hi> and to keep them <hi>ſecretly</hi> in a Pavilion, from <hi>the ſtrife of Tongues,</hi> Pſal. 31.20.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:109969:12"/>
            <p>Thirdly and Laſtly, He is <hi>with</hi> you to <hi>bleſs</hi> you, and <hi>to reward</hi> you for that <hi>good</hi> which is at any time <hi>done</hi> by you: There's no man that does any thing <hi>for</hi> God, that ſhall be a looſer <hi>by</hi> him, but ſhall have it abundantly recompenc'd <hi>to</hi> him. Thoſe that are with <hi>Him,</hi> he will be ſure to be with <hi>them;</hi> and thoſe that Honour <hi>Him, He</hi> will <hi>Honour:</hi> Thoſe that are for <hi>him,</hi> to <hi>Serve</hi> him, he will be for <hi>them,</hi> to <hi>Crown</hi> them, and to beſtow a full <hi>Reward</hi> upom them; <hi>Ye judge</hi> not for Man, but for <hi>the Lord;</hi> and ye <hi>receive</hi> not from Man, but <hi>from the Lord,</hi> as that which <hi>is chiefly</hi> conſiderable. <hi>What ever good any man doth, the ſame ſhall he receive from the Lord, whether he be Bond or Free,</hi> Eph. 6.8. To be ſure he ſhall not <hi>loſe</hi> his Reward, nor his <hi>Labour be in vain.</hi> And therefore that which is here expreſt by <hi>Gods being with you,</hi> ſome Tranſlations render it, <hi>Quod in vos redundabit,</hi> that is, which ſhall at laſt turn to <hi>your own account.</hi> And thus have we ſeen how many wayes God is ſaid <hi>to be</hi> with thoſe who are his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> in ſuch buſineſſes as theſe are, To <hi>obſerve</hi> them, to <hi>aſſist</hi> them, to <hi>defend</hi> them, and to <hi>beſtow a bleſſing</hi> upon them: And accordingly it ſhews how far it is both to be <hi>purſued,</hi> and alſo <hi>acknowledged</hi> by ſuch kind of perſons, not onely to partake of Gods <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and eſſential</hi> preſence, in regard whereof he is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109969:12"/>ſaid to be with all <hi>his Creatures;</hi> but alſo to partake of Gods <hi>ſpecial</hi> and <hi>gracious</hi> preſence, in regard whereof he is ſaid to be with thoſe who <hi>are his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>foundation</hi> of this, is <hi>Immanuel,</hi> who is, <hi>God with us:</hi> Firſt, <hi>With</hi> us, in our <hi>nature,</hi> which is reconciled to God <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> who hath taken it upon <hi>himſelf;</hi> and then <hi>with</hi> us in our <hi>Perſons,</hi> who are <hi>in Covenant</hi> with God through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> upon compliance with <hi>Evangelical Conditions:</hi> And then alſo laſt of all with us, <hi>in our Services and Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</hi> as <hi>coming</hi> from ſuch <hi>Perſons.</hi> And ſo now I have done with the <hi>firſt general</hi> part of the Text, which is the <hi>Truth declared:</hi> And that conſiſting of <hi>two</hi> Branches, Firſt, The <hi>Propoſition, Ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord.</hi> And ſecondly, The <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification,</hi> who <hi>is with you in the Judgment.</hi> And this in the nature of the <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second is the <hi>Caution inferr'd</hi> upon the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> and Declaration of this Truth, <hi>Take heed what ye do;</hi> and this in the nature of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Now this again it may be looked upon by us <hi>two</hi> manner of wayes; Firſt, In its <hi>ſimple Injunction.</hi> And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, In its <hi>rational Inference.</hi> The ſimple <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction,</hi> that is conſiderable in the <hi>words themſelves.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109969:13"/>The <hi>rational Inference,</hi> that is conſiderable in the <hi>connexion</hi> of theſe words with the <hi>other,</hi> knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Cauſal <hi>For.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſpeak of them as they lie in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and in the <hi>ſimple Injunction;</hi> Here's a <hi>Caution</hi> given to the Judges, To <hi>take heed what they do;</hi> where, by the way, before we go any further, give me leave to put in this, that when we ſay here to <hi>the Judges,</hi> we are not to take theſe <hi>Judges</hi> in the <hi>limited</hi> ſenſe only, but in the <hi>extended;</hi> nor in the <hi>Peculiar</hi> ſenſe only, but in the <hi>Comprehenſive;</hi> not only for ſuch Perſons as are the <hi>prime and principal</hi> in Judicature, and have the <hi>chief</hi> managing of it, whom we call by a ſpecial Eminency, <hi>The Juſtices of the Aſſize,</hi> (though theſe <hi>eſpecially</hi>) but alſo all <hi>others,</hi> who by their Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are any way <hi>ſubſervient</hi> or <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to them. Even <hi>they</hi> do likewiſe come within <hi>this compaſs,</hi> and have this Charge given unto them, <hi>Juſtices of Peace, Witneſſes, Jurors, Pleaders,</hi> and all others, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, who do any thing contribute to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration <hi>of Juſtice:</hi> It is that which does indeed concern <hi>all</hi> men whoſoever <hi>at large.</hi> There's no man that does <hi>any</hi> thing at all, but it be hoves him <hi>to take heed what be does,</hi> becauſe every man is <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable</hi> to God for whatſoever is done by him: But it concerns thoſe who are the <hi>Diſpenſers of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109969:13"/>Juſtice,</hi> to take this heed above all others; for which cauſe they are called upon to do ſo: To take heed, and to <hi>ſee</hi> what they do, as the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> properly ſignifies, that is, to be well inform'd, and to have good <hi>Evidence</hi> for what is done by them</p>
            <p>The <hi>giving of Caution,</hi> it does alwayes, or at leaſt, for the moſt part, ſuppoſe ſome kind <hi>of danger,</hi> which is incident to thoſe <hi>perſons</hi> to whom it is given, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there were no <hi>need</hi> at all for the giving of it; Now there is a <hi>double</hi> danger which ſuch are expoſed to, who are imploy'd in the affairs of <hi>Judicature:</hi> The one is danger <hi>of</hi> miſcarrying, and the other is danger <hi>from</hi> miſcarrying. There's danger <hi>of</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying, <hi>leſt</hi> they ſhould do ſo; and there's danger <hi>from</hi> miſcarrying, <hi>if</hi> they ſhould do ſo; where there is <hi>either</hi> or <hi>both</hi> of theſe, we do uſually <hi>give,</hi> and are willing to receive, <hi>Caution</hi> and Praemonition.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Danger <hi>of</hi> miſcarrying, there's a great deal of <hi>this</hi> in this buſineſs: The work of <hi>Judgment</hi> is ſuch a <hi>nice</hi> and intricate buſineſs, and hath ſo many <hi>Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties</hi> and Perplexities oftentimes belonging unto it; that if there be not a great deal of <hi>care</hi> taken about it, it is the <hi>eaſieſt</hi> thing that can be to miſcarry <hi>in it.</hi> Beſides that, thoſe who are exerciſed in it, are for the moſt part lyable to great <hi>Temptations</hi> on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109969:14"/>every ſide; which do call for the greater <hi>vigilancy</hi> and circumſpection <hi>in</hi> them, and give them occaſion for <hi>looking about</hi> them in thoſe things which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken by them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Danger <hi>from</hi> miſcarrying, there is much of <hi>that</hi> likewiſe in it, being a matter of very great <hi>conſequence</hi> and concernment in it's own <hi>nature.</hi> And this is a moſt ſure rule and obſervation, That <hi>thoſe</hi> things which are moſt <hi>excellent</hi> in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and right improvement, are commonly moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in their <hi>miſcarrying</hi> and diſappointment: Thus it is here in this <hi>buſineſs</hi> whereof we now ſpeak, as to the <hi>administration of Juſtice.</hi> Foraſmuch as there is a great deal <hi>of good</hi> which comes (as I have ſhewen before) from it's proceeding <hi>regularly;</hi> there is conſequently a great deal of <hi>danger</hi> and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief inſuing from its <hi>prevarication;</hi> Danger to the <hi>Judges</hi> themſelves, danger to the <hi>Perſons</hi> who are <hi>judged by</hi> them, danger to the <hi>whole State</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty it ſelf; not onely mens lives, but their Souls ſometimes hazarded by it. All which laid together, do give ground for this <hi>hint</hi> which is here exhibited to them, of <hi>taking heed what they do,</hi> which indeed we may take in the notion either of a <hi>Caution,</hi> or of a <hi>Commination;</hi> of a <hi>Caution</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition,</hi> that they <hi>might</hi> not do amiſs: And of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109969:14"/>a <hi>Commination</hi> or Threatning, if they <hi>did</hi> ſo.</p>
            <p>Whiles it is ſaid here, <hi>Take heed what ye do;</hi> we are moreover to take this expreſſion, as in the full latitude and extent <hi>of Perſons</hi> (as I hinted before) that is to ſay, both of the <hi>principal</hi> Judges, and the <hi>ſubordinate; of themſelves,</hi> and of any <hi>other</hi> that are <hi>ſubſervient</hi> to them; ſo we are likewiſe to take it in the full latitude and extent <hi>of things,</hi> and of the <hi>Office</hi> belonging to ſuch Perſons to be diſcharged by them, where there are <hi>two</hi> things eſpecially as pertinent and belonging hereunto, and branches hereof: The <hi>one</hi> is as to matter <hi>of Condemnation,</hi> and the other as to matter <hi>of Abſolution;</hi> Theſe <hi>two</hi> eſpecially do make up the work of <hi>Judges,</hi> who to ſpeak in the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> to this purpoſe, are for the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of thoſe that do <hi>Evil,</hi> and for the <hi>Praiſe</hi> of them that <hi>do well,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. And ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and his Power: If thou doeſt <hi>well</hi> (ſayes he) thou ſhalt have <hi>Praiſe</hi> of the ſame. But if thou doſt <hi>Evil,</hi> he is an <hi>Avenger</hi> to execute <hi>Wrath, Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4. So then in reference to each of theſe Parts and Branches of Judicature, we ſee how this Caution lies, and how far forth it is to be underſtood by us: As it referrs to matter <hi>of Condemnation;</hi> So take heed what ye do there, that ye do not <hi>Condemn the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent:</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:109969:15"/>And as it refers to matter of Abſolution, ſo take heed alſo what ye do there, that ye do not <hi>aqcuit the Guilty;</hi> for there's a miſcarriage and danger <hi>in both:</hi> He <hi>that juſtifieth the Wicked,</hi> and he <hi>that condemneth the just,</hi> even they <hi>both are an abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 17.15.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then <hi>take heed what ye do,</hi> that is, that ye do not <hi>condemn the innocent;</hi> Take heed <hi>of that,</hi> remember that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> which he hath to this purpoſe, <hi>That Rulers are not for a Terrour to good Works, but onely to the Evil,</hi> Rom. 13.3. that is, ſtill they are not ſo <hi>ex Officio,</hi> &amp; by <hi>their Places,</hi> which inclines them <hi>otherwiſe:</hi> And therefore it is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that thoſe who are <hi>good,</hi> ſhould not be <hi>afraid of their Power,</hi> becauſe in ſtead of being <hi>checked</hi> and reproved, and <hi>condemned by</hi> them, they ſhould rather (as it is there expreſt) <hi>have praiſe from</hi> them. Thus it ought to be in this particular, and for this purpoſe a great deal <hi>of care</hi> and heed to be had about it, leſt men ſhould fall under <hi>that cenſure</hi> which St. <hi>James</hi> faſtens upon ſome perſons, Ye have <hi>condemned and killed the Juſt, and he doth not reſiſt you,</hi> James 5.6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Take heed what ye do, that is, that ye do not <hi>acquit the Guilty:</hi> There's a Care to be had of <hi>that</hi> likewiſe. As <hi>Innocency</hi> is to be <hi>cheriſhed</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109969:15"/>protected; ſo <hi>is Vice</hi> alſo to be <hi>diſcountenanced</hi> and puniſhed, which is <hi>another</hi> branch of the <hi>Office</hi> of ſuch Perſons as are in place of <hi>Judicature, For the Puniſhment of thoſe that do evil,</hi> as was expreſt in the Scripture above-mentioned. This is that which lies upon them, to be careful of in themſelves, and to <hi>take heed</hi> that nothing may <hi>hinder</hi> them, or take them off <hi>from</hi> it; whether <hi>fear of Diſpleaſure,</hi> or <hi>hope of Reward,</hi> or <hi>remiſneſs of Spirit,</hi> or <hi>inordinate Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> or what ever elſe we might name, as might be <hi>obſtructive</hi> hereunto: Although there is alwayes <hi>a tenderneſs</hi> to be had as to the <hi>managing</hi> of ſuch Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and a ſenſibleneſs of <hi>humane infirmity</hi> and common frailty; yet as for the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf, it cannot be ſafely neglected or omitted by ſuch kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are intruſted with it. There's a great deal <hi>of miſchief</hi> which follows upon the intermiſſion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of <hi>Juſtice</hi> in this particular, when as <hi>convicted Offenders</hi> are not brought <hi>to condign Puniſhment:</hi> For from hence are men ſo much the more <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd</hi> and confirm'd in Sin, and incouraged to the Commiſſion <hi>of</hi> it, according to that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11. <hi>Becauſe Sentence againſt an evil Work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the Hearts of the Sons of Men are fully ſet in them to do Evil. Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> it <hi>improves</hi> from <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and the more that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109969:16"/>men are <hi>favour'd</hi> in it, the more earneſtly are they ſet <hi>upon</hi> it, and addicted <hi>to it;</hi> which makes ſo much the more for ſuch a Courſe as this is to be taken with it.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Caution</hi> was never more <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi> then in theſe <hi>Times</hi> wherein we live, in which Sin is come to that <hi>height</hi> and extremity as it is amongſt us in all <hi>particulars;</hi> In <hi>Filthineſs,</hi> in <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> in <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury,</hi> in <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> and in all manner of <hi>Profaneneſs.</hi> And theſe alſo carryed on with an <hi>high Hand,</hi> with a <hi>brazen Face,</hi> with a <hi>bold Fore-head:</hi> The <hi>Impudence</hi> of Sin in this Age, makes it to be <hi>notorious and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable;</hi> wherein People are ſo far from being <hi>aſhamed</hi> of it, as that they rather glory <hi>in it,</hi> and make their boaſts <hi>of it,</hi> counting it an advantage to them to make <hi>Others</hi> as bad <hi>as themſelves;</hi> becauſe they think that whiles Sin is more <hi>common,</hi> it will be leſs <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> as having <hi>many</hi> to plead for it. Give me leave to inſtance <hi>in one Sin</hi> amongſt the reſt, which there are very good <hi>Laws</hi> againſt, and it is pitty but they were put <hi>into Execution,</hi> and that is your <hi>common and profane Swearing</hi> and Curſing, and <hi>hideous Blaſphemy,</hi> whereby the great and glorious <hi>Name of God</hi> is in a moſt fearful and execrable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>rent</hi> and torn in pieces: We cannot paſs the Streets, but our Ears are ready <hi>to tingle</hi> at the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109969:16"/>of ſuch <hi>horrid Oaths</hi> as are utter'd in every cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. A <hi>Sin</hi> which is the more <hi>intollerable,</hi> as it is leſs <hi>accountable,</hi> which men have nothing to ſay for themſelves in the defence of it, as having no provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or <hi>temptation</hi> at all to it, but onely the <hi>naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs</hi> and perverſeneſs of their own <hi>Hearts;</hi> who will be <hi>wicked</hi> becauſe they <hi>will</hi> be, and are <hi>reſolved</hi> in themſelves ſo <hi>to</hi> be, let there come <hi>on</hi> it what there <hi>will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this does very much call for the <hi>reſtraint</hi> of thoſe that have <hi>Power to</hi> reſtrain it; <hi>An bainous Crime, and an Iniquity to be puniſhed by the Judges:</hi> To uſe that expreſſion, <hi>Job</hi> 31.11. and ſo for all <hi>other</hi> Sins beſides, which do come within their compaſs. This <hi>Caution</hi> here in the <hi>Text,</hi> it reaches them in <hi>this</hi> particular, To <hi>take heed what they do,</hi> yea, and to take heed what they do <hi>not</hi> do too, which is <hi>included</hi> alſo in it: For even <hi>ſimple omiſſions</hi> are <hi>very dangerous</hi> in ſuch caſes as theſe are. In <hi>times</hi> of common and <hi>publick Corruption,</hi> and the ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of wickedneſs in the World, there are <hi>two ſorts</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> eſpecially which are very highly <hi>concern'd,</hi> and cannot eaſily diſcharge themſelves from <hi>Guilt,</hi> in the <hi>neglect</hi> of their Duties about it; <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters. Miniſters</hi> whiles they neglect to <hi>reprove</hi> it, they become guilty of it by their <hi>ſilence.</hi> And <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:109969:17"/>while they neglect to <hi>puniſh</hi> it, they become guilty of it by their <hi>Indulgence.</hi> And it is an <hi>heavy</hi> and grievous thing to draw the burden <hi>of other</hi> mens Sins upon our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and to partake with them <hi>in</hi> them, which we do by our connivance <hi>at</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore all both <hi>one</hi> and <hi>t'other</hi> be awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and exhorted in this particular, <hi>To take heed what we do;</hi> that ſo our <hi>examples</hi> may have an influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon our <hi>Offices</hi> in the <hi>ſuccesfulneſs</hi> of them, and both together upon the good of the <hi>State and Kingdome</hi> wherein we live; which we are all of us concern'd in to preſerve it what we can in <hi>innocency,</hi> that we may preſerve it what we can <hi>from ruine:</hi> For <hi>Righteouſneſs exalts a Nation, but Sin is a reproach to any People,</hi> as it is in <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34.</p>
            <p>And moreover, let us look to <hi>our Hearts and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> in all theſe things; which is eſpecially to be regarded by us. Take heed not onely <hi>what</hi> ye do, but <hi>how</hi> ye do it; which we are alſo for the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of the ſenſe to take in, as <hi>included</hi> in this <hi>Caution.</hi> Man looks to the <hi>outward appearance,</hi> but the <hi>Lord</hi> looks unto the <hi>Heart:</hi> It is poſſible to be very <hi>unjuſt</hi> even in the execution of <hi>Juſtice</hi> it ſelf, according to the <hi>ſpirit and principle</hi> which men are at any time carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>by</hi> in the diſcharge of it; for which reaſon it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them to be the more <hi>wary</hi> and watchful over
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109969:17"/>themſelves. And ſo much may ſuffice to have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of this paſſage in the <hi>firſt</hi> view and notion of it, as it is conſiderable in the <hi>words themſelves,</hi> or ſimple <hi>Injunction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, as it is conſiderable in the <hi>connexion</hi> of theſe words with the <hi>other,</hi> or in their <hi>rational inference</hi> expreſt in the cauſal <hi>For;</hi> becauſe, or foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, <hi>Ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the Judgment; therefore,</hi> and upon <hi>this</hi> account and conſideration, <hi>Take heed what ye do:</hi> where again, we are to take the branches <hi>diſtinctly</hi> and ſeparately one from the other, and ſo the <hi>inference</hi> in each <hi>reference</hi> both to the <hi>propoſition</hi> and to the <hi>amplification:</hi> In reference to the <hi>propoſition</hi> thus, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye <hi>judge not for Man, but for the Lord;</hi> For there is the force of an argument in both; therefore <hi>take heed</hi> what ye do, for <hi>that</hi> reaſon. Again, in reference to the <hi>amplification</hi> thus, becauſe the <hi>Lord is with you</hi> in the Judgment: Therefore take heed what ye do <hi>for that alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Take it in the <hi>firſt</hi> reference, namely, as to the <hi>propoſition,</hi> thus, <hi>Take heed what ye do,</hi> becauſe ye judge <hi>not for Man, but for the Lord:</hi> Where we may firſt of all in general take notice of the <hi>Topick</hi> or <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Argument,</hi> which is here uſed; and that as taken not ſo much from <hi>Humane,</hi> as from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109969:18"/>
               <hi>Divine</hi> conſiderations; from <hi>God</hi> himſelf rather than <hi>from Man.</hi> And it gives us by the way an hint of the diſpoſition of each party; both of the perſon that uſed it, and of the perſons to whom it was uſed. Firſt, For the perſon that <hi>uſed</hi> it, which was <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> we ſee what <hi>kind</hi> of arguments were moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual <hi>with</hi> him, by what was uſed <hi>by</hi> him: There are ſome that would have dealt with theſe Judges upon <hi>civil and ſecular</hi> conſiderations, and in a way of <hi>Policy;</hi> but <hi>he</hi> deals with them rather upon <hi>ſacred</hi> and religious conſiderations, and in <hi>a</hi> way of <hi>Piety.</hi> Thoſe things which moſt prevail with <hi>men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> they are apt commonly to urge upon <hi>others,</hi> from the <hi>ſenſe</hi> and efficacy which they have of them upon their <hi>own Hearts:</hi> And ſo here.</p>
            <p>Again, For the <hi>Perſons</hi> to whom this Argument was uſed: Theſe <hi>Judges</hi> they were probably <hi>pious</hi> and religious men, and ſuch as truly <hi>feared God,</hi> or elſe <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> would never have uſed ſuch an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument as this was to them: Reaſons taken from <hi>Piety</hi> are <hi>inſignificant</hi> to an <hi>impious Heart,</hi> and carry no ſtroke at all of prevalency with them. Carnal and <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> people, who have <hi>no ſenſe</hi> of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all in them, nor <hi>no ſear</hi> of God before their eyes; they will ſooner <hi>ſcoff</hi> and <hi>mock</hi> at ſuch argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and reaſons as theſe, then be any thing moved
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109969:18"/>or wrought upon by them. But theſe perſons here in the Text, as we may conjecture were <hi>better</hi> affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And ſo this argument which was uſed unto them, it was <hi>proper</hi> for them: It was <hi>Argumentum ad Homines,</hi> though not <hi>Argumentum ab Hominibus.</hi> And this we may obſerve from the <hi>Condition of</hi> the argument in <hi>general.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to come more cloſely to it in <hi>particular, Ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord; therefore</hi> take heed what ye do: The argument holds good in this <hi>connexion</hi> upon a <hi>various</hi> conſideration, we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it into theſe following <hi>Improvements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Ye judge for <hi>the Lord,</hi> and it is He that <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes</hi> you; Therefore take heed what ye do, that ſo thereby ye may <hi>diſcharge your Truſt,</hi> and approve your ſelves to him chiefly who is your <hi>Maſter,</hi> and that ſots <hi>you on Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Ye judge <hi>for the Lord,</hi> and it is He that is repreſented <hi>by</hi> you, and in whoſe <hi>place</hi> ye ſtand; Therefore <hi>take heed what ye do,</hi> that ye may do that which is every way <hi>ſutable</hi> and agreeable to ſuch an <hi>excellent Perſon</hi> as He indeed is: This <hi>Picture</hi> is to be like <hi>the Perſon;</hi> and the <hi>Image</hi> is as near as may be, to be proportionable to the <hi>Samplar.</hi> Thoſe who are Gods by <hi>Title and Appellation,</hi> as Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Judges are, they ſhould as much as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109969:19"/>poſſibly might be, be <hi>Gods</hi> alſo in <hi>property and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition:</hi> That ſo it may be ſaid <hi>of them</hi> as was it ſaid of <hi>Paul and Barnabas</hi> at <hi>Lyſtra, The Gods are come down to us in the likeneſs of Men,</hi> Acts 14.11. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they bear the <hi>Name</hi> of God, ſuſtain the <hi>Place,</hi> repreſent the <hi>Perſon,</hi> they ſhould therefore, as near as they can, partake of the <hi>Nature,</hi> and ſo carry themſelves in point of Judicature even as <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf does. And thus we find it improved in the <hi>verſe</hi> immediately <hi>following</hi> the Text, the <hi>ſeventh</hi> verſe of this <hi>Chapter, Wherefore now let the fear of the LORD be upon you, take heed and do it; For there is no Iniquity with the Lord our God, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons, nor taking of Gifts.</hi> The <hi>Deputies</hi> and Vicegerents are to be true and faithful to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom <hi>they repreſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Ye judge for the <hi>Lord,</hi> as the Perſon that is eſpecially <hi>aym'd</hi> at and intended in your Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature; and therefore be careful that ye fall not ſhort of that <hi>main End</hi> whereunto ye are <hi>deſign'd;</hi> and eſpecially that ye walk not <hi>contrary to</hi> it. There is ſomewhat conſiderable in reference <hi>to Man,</hi> which in ſome reſpects might prevail with you to <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection</hi> and exactneſs in your proceedings. But this conſideration, which is taken <hi>from God,</hi> is the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> of all, and ſo moſt of all to be <hi>minded</hi> by you.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109969:19"/>For as old <hi>Ely</hi> ſpake ſometime to his <hi>Sons</hi> to this purpoſe in 2 Sam. 2.25. <hi>If one man ſin againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Judge ſhall judge him:</hi> But if <hi>a man ſin againſt the Lord, who ſhall intreat for him.</hi> And thus does the <hi>Inference</hi> hold good in its firſt refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as it is carryed in the <hi>ſimple Propoſition,</hi> Ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord; therefore take heed what ye do, for that reaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It holds alſo in reference to the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional <hi>amplification, Who is with you in the Judgment,</hi> and that according to all thoſe explications which we have before given of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He is with you <hi>to behold</hi> you; therefore take heed what ye do, as thoſe who are accountable <hi>to him,</hi> for that which ſhall <hi>be done by you</hi> Thoſe who are now Judges of <hi>others,</hi> they muſt hereafter be judged <hi>themſelves,</hi> and together with thoſe whom they judge, ſtand <hi>perſonally</hi> before <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Tribunal:</hi> Whereof theſe inferior <hi>Judicatures</hi> are both a <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation,</hi> and alſo an <hi>Aſſurance.</hi> Therefore there are ſome Tranſlators who thus render thoſe words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Pſal 82.1. where it is ſaid, He judgeth <hi>among</hi> the Gods: <hi>They read</hi> it, In <hi>the midſt he will judge</hi> the Gods. Intimating thus much unto us, That the <hi>great God of all,</hi> he <hi>will judge</hi> theſe little and <hi>petty</hi> gods, which now have <hi>his Name upon</hi> them; And ſo <hi>he will.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:109969:20"/>
            <p>Secondly, He <hi>is with you</hi> to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> you, Therefore take heed what ye do, as careful to <hi>improve that help</hi> and aſſiſtance which he <hi>offers to you: Inablement</hi> is an ingagement to <hi>performance,</hi> and the more <hi>help</hi> at any time we have, the leſs <hi>excuſable</hi> are we in <hi>ſayling</hi> of that <hi>Duty</hi> which is required of us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He is with you <hi>to defend you;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>take heed what ye do,</hi> that ſo ye may give him <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> to defend you <hi>ſtill,</hi> and teſtifie your <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> for his <hi>former</hi> defending of you: His protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not to make you the more <hi>ſecure,</hi> but rather the more <hi>careful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, He is with you <hi>to reward you;</hi> Therefore <hi>take heed what ye do,</hi> that ſo he may beſtow a <hi>full</hi> reward upon you: That when the <hi>chief Judge</hi> of all ſhall <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,</hi> you alſo may appear <hi>with him,</hi> and <hi>receive a Crown of Glory</hi> that <hi>fadeth not away:</hi> Even a <hi>Crown of Juſtice</hi> and Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge</hi> ſhall give you <hi>in that day;</hi> and not <hi>to you</hi> onely, but alſo to all them that <hi>love his appearing.</hi> And thus ye have the <hi>Caution inferr'd</hi> upon the <hi>Truth declared,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> which follows upon the <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there is but <hi>one</hi> thing more behind, which yet is very <hi>conſiderable,</hi> for the better <hi>inforcing</hi> of all the reſt; which though it <hi>be first</hi> in the <hi>order</hi> of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109969:20"/>
               <hi>Text,</hi> yet I have reſerved it to the <hi>laſt,</hi> as carrying a very <hi>good cloſe</hi> with it. And that is <hi>the Preface</hi> or Introduction, in theſe words, <hi>And he ſaid unto the Judges,</hi> which hath the greater <hi>Emphaſis</hi> with it, as it does exhibit to us <hi>the Perſon</hi> by <hi>whom</hi> this Charge is given; And that is <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> who muſt not be omitted by us; we may look upon him as conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of us, under a <hi>various Reduplication,</hi> and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo very <hi>pertinent</hi> to the <hi>matter and buſineſs</hi> in hand.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As he was a <hi>good</hi> Man, and one that did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>take heed</hi> what he did, therefore he might the better call upon <hi>others</hi> to do ſo: <hi>Guilt</hi> is an obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Duty,</hi> and eſpecially to good <hi>Counſel,</hi> both in the <hi>performance,</hi> and alſo <hi>in the ſucceſs.</hi> But thoſe who are <hi>themſelves</hi> careful and <hi>exact</hi> in their <hi>own</hi> Converſation, they may with the greater <hi>freedome</hi> and confidence adviſe <hi>others;</hi> and their <hi>advice</hi> will from thence prove to be the more <hi>effectual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As he was a <hi>great</hi> Man, and one that had the <hi>command of</hi> them: He was a <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>where the word of a King is, there is power,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.4. Not onely theſe Judges <hi>Piety,</hi> but their <hi>Loyally</hi> was concern'd in this <hi>buſineſs. Good Counſel</hi> it would not be <hi>rejected</hi> from the <hi>meaneſt</hi> perſon; but when beſides the preſſing <hi>matter</hi> and nature of the <hi>things</hi> required, there ſhall be an acceſſion of the Authority
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109969:21"/>of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> alſo requiring them, there is a <hi>double</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement. As one who may in Chriſt enjoyn that which is convenient, <hi>Philemon</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As he was the Perſon that <hi>inſtituted,</hi> and ſet <hi>up</hi> theſe Judges: It was he that gave them their task, that <hi>injoyn'd them,</hi> and put them upon this Service. Therefore he thought himſelf ſo much the more <hi>concern'd</hi> in their <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and managing</hi> of it. Thoſe that at any time put others into Places <hi>of Truſt</hi> and Publick Imployment, whether <hi>of Magiſtracy</hi> or <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> are ſo much the <hi>more ingaged</hi> in their faithful diſcharge of them, as they are themſelves <hi>occaſions</hi> of them to them, as undertaking them upon <hi>their account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly and Laſtly, As he was one that had lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a <hi>check</hi> from God <hi>himſelf,</hi> for his own <hi>ſinful compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> in the <hi>ſecond</hi> verſe of this Chapter: He was from hence now ſo much the more careful <hi>to warn</hi> and admonish <hi>others.</hi> Thoſe who have at any time felt <hi>the ſmart</hi> of Sin in their <hi>own</hi> Conſciences, will be the more <hi>ſollicitous</hi> to keep off their <hi>Brethren</hi> from falling into the <hi>like</hi> miſcarriages <hi>with</hi> them, and the ill conſequents <hi>of</hi> them.</p>
            <p>And thus now have ye this <hi>whole Text</hi> in the <hi>ſeveral parts</hi> and branches of it, both the <hi>Preface</hi> and the <hi>Principal</hi> Matter. The <hi>Charge</hi> which is given, with the <hi>Perſon</hi> giving this Charge, and from both together a <hi>ſpecial</hi> ingagement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Perſons</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> it is given: Here's no place for <hi>any excuſe,</hi> or <hi>evaſion of</hi> Duty. They could not plead <hi>Ignorance,</hi> that they did not <hi>know</hi> it, for they are here <hi>inſtructed.</hi> They could not plead <hi>Forgetfulneſs,</hi> that they did not <hi>mind it,</hi> for they are here <hi>admoniſh'd:</hi> And not onely theſe perſons <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> but all <hi>others</hi> in the like places <hi>with</hi> them; they may take theſe words of the Text as ſpoken <hi>to</hi> them, and make uſe <hi>of</hi> them. That as I <hi>began,</hi> ſo I may <hi>end, Take heed what ye do, for ye judge not for Man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the Judg-ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
